Today's דף *daf* is ע"ג *Ayin Gimmel* seventy-three. Excuse me I said
I did it wrong ע"ד *Ayin Daled* seventy-four and
but we start in the middle of ע"ג עמוד ב׳ *Ayin Gimmel
Amud Bet*, we didn't finish yesterday. In any way, a few words
of introduction are appropriate because we have been spending a lot of
time building up for this משנה *Mishna*. This משנה *Mishna* lists the
thirty-nine מלאכות melachot *Melachot* as I had mentioned yesterday. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* actually many times has quoted the first line of this משנה
*Mishna* before getting to it, building up the anticipation and as I
discovered actually I checked that there were six times it quoted the
משנה *Mishna* before getting up to it and then a seventh time
right after getting up to it, similar to the six props leading
up and this is really the central location, the listing of the
thirty-nine categories of מלאכה melacha, *Melacha* was the משנה *Mishna* in ע"ג
עמוד א׳ *Ayin Gimmel Amud Aleph*. And we will be seeing as
we go through the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doing it bit by bit
and looking at each category. Somewhat ironically and even a little I
would say frustratingly, the discussion around each one of the מלאכות melachot,
*Melachot* can sometimes be extremely terse. Sometimes it's terse here because in
later פרקים *Prakim* there will be a greater development of that category
of מלאכה melacha *Melacha*. Sometimes it's just terse period and there's very
little material in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about what that category of
מלאכה melacha. *Melacha* is and its exact parameters. And I really have
no way of explaining this why we have extensive discussion about purely
theoretical issues about how many חטאות chataot *Chata'ot* you bring and like
extensive discussion about, you know, wearing things on שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* and
all these various issues and then when you actually get to the
ל"ט מלאכות Melachot, *Lamed Tet Melachot* really sometimes only a few lines
of גמרא Gemara *Gemara* for each of the מלאכות Melachot, *Melachot*. But
again maybe at least some of them do get elaborated on, that's
really what the rest of the מסכת masechet. *Masechet* is, sometimes on
the דאורייתא De'oraisa *De-Oraita* parameters, sometimes the דרבנן De'rabbanan. *De-Rabbanan* parameters, sometimes
it's not clear if we're talking דאורייתא de'oraisa. *De-Oraita* or דרבנן derabbanan,
*De-Rabbanan*, but just to give you a warning that as we take
apart this משנה *Mishna* we might we will find really sometimes only
a very short discussion. What we did yesterday is we listed the
thirty-nine מלאכות *Melachot*. As I pointed out at the time they really
break down into four categories: the process of making bread which is
eleven מלאכות *Melachot*, the process of making a garment which is thirteen,
the process
of making a type of a book קלף *Klaf* and having things
written on it is nine, and the process of building a house,
of building things. So you got your clothes, you got your food,
you got your domicile and of course what else does a Jew
need but his books? So anyway those are that gets you thirty-eight
and then the last one carrying which doesn't fall directly into that
category. And as we said at that time the assumption we always
work with and the assumption we're going to see today in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is that these are part related to what they
did in the משכן Mishkan, *Mishkan*. And as such even though this
is not exactly what they did in the this is not exactly
how they categorized what they did in the משכן Mishkan. *Mishkan*, where
did this link? When did this happen in the משכן Mishkan, *Mishkan*?
When did that happen in the משכן Mishkan, *Mishkan*? Nevertheless it's an
organizing principle, a nice way of thinking of of categorizing what those
thirty-nine מלאכות *Melachot* are. That being said I want to remind you,
I reminded you yesterday, I remind you again today the position of
the יראים Yereim, *Yereim* that says that it's actually according to one
approach in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* it is not based on what
was in the משכן Mishkan *Mishkan*. Based on one of the approaches
we learned a while ago about the thirty-nine מלאכות *Melachot* it is
just based on what is מלאכה melacha. *Melacha*, what חז"ל's *Chazal's* concepts
of work was. And if they looked out into the larger world
and they saw that these are the main ways in which people
sort of, you know, interacted and did constructive labor in the world.
And so these categories are not just organizational categories, they actually are
the reasons why these are the מלאכות *Melachot*. So that's a quite
radically different approach that we're normally not taught but that is the
way the יראים *Yereim* understand one approach in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
So I'll get you with that. So anyway the other thing again
this is just a review because we did a lot yesterday. So
the other thing that's important to know is that the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* discusses certain אבות avot? *Avot* and תולדות toldot, *Toldot*. And to
remind ourselves what is a תולדה toladah. *Tolda*, what is a descendant
from the main parent category? And normally a descendant is something that
is similar in one way to the אב av. *Av*. The אב
av *Av* either in terms of form or in terms of function.
So for example
baking and cooking and frying those all are very similar in terms
of purpose and function, using heat to make food. Occasionally there are
some things that we'll see that could be similar in form but
not function like grinding sawdust is similar to, you know, making wheat
out of a kernel of wheat, making flour out of a kernel
of wheat. So it's similar physically it takes a whole thing and
makes it into little pieces but it's not similar in terms of
what it's there to do which is like to, you know, transform
food, it's there to, you know, transform something else. And there other
types of things which are similar in function
sort of like in terms of their physically what they're doing but
not so much in terms of form, but in terms of function
I mean in terms of form but not so much in terms
of function what their goal is. You can pretty much assume that
anything that achieves a very similar goal Most of the time is
a תולדה. toldah There are exceptions, but things that are similar in
their physical process but not in terms of the goal are not
always a תולדה. toladah But those are general rules. But those are
the two things. Now if somebody is similar both in form and
in function,
then it might actually be considered not a תולדה toladah. but a
parallel אב. av And this is an idea that רש״י Rashi and
the רמב״ם Rambam have, that there's something called מעין מלאכה אחת, me'ein
melacha achat, similar of one type of a מלאכה, melacha. which means
that there are things which are all in the same אב av.
category. The אב av. category is not just one, it's more like
a set of things are the אב. av. So for example what
I said, frying and
cooking, or maybe even cooking and baking, those are pretty similar both
in terms of what they're coming to do and the process of
doing it. So that might be a parallel אב. av. Or the
גמרא Gemara says, planting a seed and planting a
tree, or even maybe
grafting a tree, even those are just ways of directly manipulating an
object that you are trying to get to grow. Something that would
be a תולדה toladah, would be let's say putting manure down, or
watering, or pruning a tree. Because there you're dealing with the surrounding
environment to encourage the growth of the thing, but not directly dealing
with the thing itself. But if it's very, very similar in all
those ways, then it might be according to רש״י Rashi and רמב״ם
Rambam this concept of a parallel אב. av Yes, Michael.
Just to clarify, according to the position of the יראים, it says
just it seems very contextually based. So if this was coming up
now, we may take what in ancient was an אב מלאכה av
melacha and then in fifty years it would fall into that. That
could be.
And he says למה מסרה הכתוב לחכמים lama mesarah hakatuv lachachamim and
once it got there, it got crystallized and that's what we have.
And no one can add.
Right, exactly. Okay. So now we move on
and we'll start with החורש. hachoresh. The other examples we had yesterday
also was like a two for one, pruning also for the sake
of the wood gets you two מלאכות and again the purpose of
counting two is that if you did it בשוגג beshogeg you'd bring
two קרבנות. korbanot. You can't kill somebody twice. Now so we dealt
with חורש choresh and זורע, zoreia, and we dealt basically with זורע,
zoreia, planting, and dealt with also pruning and so on, and now
we move on to חורש choresh to making a furrow. תנו רבנן,
Tanu rabanan, we taught in the ברייתא, braita, middle of ע״ג ע״ב.
Ayin Gimmel Amud Bet.
החורש והחופר, Hachoresh vehachofer, whether one makes a furrow or one digs,
again digs some type of a ditch, but again for the sake
of planting. והחורץ, Vehachoretz, or you make a חריץ charitz which is
also a narrow type of a ditch, all of those כולן מלאכה
אחת הן. kulan melacha achat hen. Notice it did not say these
are תולדות, toldot these are one מלאכה melacha because essentially they're all
the same thing. They're working the ground to make it more softer
and more appropriate for planting. So it's making some type of a
physical change in the ground to make it more fit for growing
things. אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, says רב ששת, Rav Sheshet,
האי סילוקא דגבשושית hai siluka d'gavshushit ונטלה. unatalah. So let's say you
had a mound of earth and you removed it to smooth the
ground. If it was בבית bevayit in your house, they had dirt
floors, חייב משום בונה, chayav mishum boneh, then what you've done is
you have the דין din of בונה. boneh. You have done a
construction because you've built something, you have built the floor of your
house. If
however בשדה, besadeh, if you do it out in the field where
you grow things, חייב משום חורש. chayav mishum choresh. Then it is
for plowing. Although interestingly, plowing is making a hole and this you
didn't make a hole, you actually flattened something, but nevertheless, again conceptually
it is working the ground, doing something to the ground to make
it appropriate for planting. So if that's out in a context where
it's appropriate for planting, out in the field, that's חורש, choresh, even
though it's not a hole. This would probably be a תולדה. toldah
Maybe not though, who knows? Again, it's directly on the ground, it's
making it fit, it's hard to know, maybe this is a parallel
אב. av But if it's in a house, then even though you
took something down rather than built something up, anybody ever built a
house, leveling the ground is a major part of the construction process.
So therefore that is construction and that is בונה. boneh. Okay. אמר
רבי אבא, Amar Rabbi Abba, החופר גומא בשבת hachofer guma b'Shabbat ואינו
צריך אלא לאפרה. v'eino tzarich ela l'afrah. Now here, did I skip
a line? I skipped a line. Okay. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says
רבא, Rava, האי סילוקא דגומא, hai siluka d'guma, a similar example and
this is even more that it's not digging a hole, you had
a hole וטממה v'timemah and you filled it. So you leveled it
by filling a hole. בבית חייב משום בונה, Bevayit chayav mishum boneh,
in the house you're חייב chayav because of building, again you made
a floor. ובשדה חייב משום חורש, Uvasadeh chayav mishum choresh, and in
the field because of חורש choresh because again even though you didn't
make a hole, but you directly changed the topography and you worked
the ground to make it more fit for planting. אמר
רבי אבא, Amar Rabbi Abba, now there by the way notice it's
not what your כונה kavana was, it's where it took place. We
might be talking according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that מלאכה שאינה
צריכה לגופה חייב, melacha she'eina tzricha legufa chayav, it doesn't matter what
your כונה kavana was, but we still have to objectively define what
did your action do? And the objective definition of your action of
filling a hole is different based on whether it was in the
house or whether it was in the field. אמר רבי אבא, Amar
Rabbi Abba, said Rabbi Abba,
החופר גומא בשבת ואינו צריך אלא לעפרה, hachopher gumma b'shabbos v'eino tzarich
ela l'afrah, you dug a hole on Shabbat and you only wanted
the dirt. You need your, you need dirt, you need dirt, I
don't know, because they would use dirt to cover like, you know,
messes in the house, because you know it's easier than sweeping, if
you got a dirt floor, you just throw some extra dirt on
it. Whatever it is, you needed dirt, so you made so you
wanted it for your kid's sandbox, you dug a
hole. So פטור, patur, you're exempt, there's no איסור issur for getting
dirt, I mean it's מוקצה, muktzah, but okay. The איסור issur is
for digging the hole. So why aren't you חייב chayav for digging
the hole? Because it is a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eina
tzricha legufa. And this is the classic example of the גמרא Gemara
of a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eina tzricha legufa. You did
the exact מלאכה. melacha, Somebody from the outside looks, sees you digging
a hole. From the outside perspective it looks completely like a מלאכה.
melacha. But your goal was different than the stated purpose of the
מלאכה. melacha. Stated by whom is an interesting question, but let's say
stated by the normal way in which it was done in the
משכן, Mishkan. okay? That's the general definition of מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה.
melacha she'eina tzricha legufa. So רש"י Rashi says here, in another place
רש"י Rashi says something else, but for here the מלאכה צריכה לגופה
melacha tzricha legufa as you did it for the purpose that is
not the purpose as defined by what was done in the משכן.
Mishkan. So digging a hole is a מלאכה melacha? because why? Its
goal is to either build something in the house or make something
fit for planting. Here you really are completely uninterested in the hole,
you are doing it because you want the dirt. So you're doing
the physical act for a for a different purpose, you are פטור,
patur, you are exempt. Now that normally is a debate of רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
is only the one who says you're exempt for אינה צריכה לגופה.
eina tzricha legufa. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. ואפילו
רבי יהודה, v'afillu Rabbi Yehuda, even according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
דאמר מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה חייב עליה, d'amar melacha she'eina tzricha legufa
chayav aleha,
that normally even if you do it not for its intended purpose,
you're חייב chayav because you did the same מלאכה, melacha? you dug
a hole. הני מילי מתקן, hani milei metakken,
that's only when you actually are doing something constructive. האי מקלקל הוא.
hai mekalekel hu.
Here, if you don't want a hole in your house, you don't
want a hole in the middle of the field, it's not it's
not making your floor more level and it's not making your field
more fit for planting. So then even so then it actually objectively
is not, even forgetting what your intention is, you're just making a
mess. The hole is not something that is helping making the field
more appropriate for planting later. What if you could plant in it
later? If you happen to dig it in a way that would
help you in the plant, then according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
you'd be חייב, chayav, even if that wasn't your intent. But if
basically you're just making a big hole that's a big mess, so
then even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda it's not then that is a
type of a hole that's a מקלקל, mekalkel, not a מתקן, metakken,
and even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would agree, yes.
Then my question is, you know, how much is that context dependent?
In other words, what would adults do, let's say kids though are
playing in a sandbox. They may want the hole, may not want
the hole, they may build something, they may want to knock it
down. You know what I'm saying? So does that shift at all?
I mean yes, they're making a hole, but you know what I'm
saying? Kids do different reasons, things for different reasons? Well, I mean
then you also get into what your חיוב chiyuv is vis-a-vis kids,
but presumably their intention is just is is treated the same in
terms of this. The question more maybe than what you're asking is
let's say you're doing it like without any clear thought about what
the purpose is for doing it or something of that nature, which
but that would probably, you know, and then we might sort of
say like hypothetically ניחא ליה אי לא ניחא ליה, nicha lei ei
lo nicha lei, then it gets to somewhat maybe the space between
אינה צריכה לגופה eina tzricha legufa and פסיק רישא דלא ניחא ליה.
p'sik reisha d'lo nicha lei. But anyway, but for now I'm you
know, I'm going to assume that you at least have something in
mind and
so kids shouldn't be playing in a sandbox on Shabbat?
Well, sandbox is different. No, no, no, sandbox isn't digging a hole,
sandbox is it's all loose sand. That's a different story. And it's
not מוקצה? muktzah? Yeah, because there's no hole, it's all just loose
sand.
We hold it has to be destructive or it just matters what
your intent?
No, we hold like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that if אינה צריכה
לגופה eina tzricha legufa you're פטור, patur, but it's not מותר, muttar,
you're פטור. patur. Okay. Alright. Okay,
והקוצר. v'hakotzer. So now we move on to to cutting. So we
did planting, digging, making the, you know, sort of plowing and planting,
and now we deal with harvesting, cutting growing things down, because you
know for to because you want them. Again, if you're cutting them
down for other purposes, like the גמרא Gemara had pruning, and you're
not interested in the wood, that's not קוצר. kotzer. But if you're
pruning and you do want the wood, or you're picking an apple
off of a tree, any type of thing where you pick something
that's growing and you stop it from growing because you're you want
that thing, then that is קוצר. kotzer. Now, תנא הקוצר, tanna hakotzer,
whether you are cutting like like harvesting wheat, הבוצר, habotzer, whether you
are harvesting grapes, והגודר, v'hagoder, or whether it is dates, והמסיק, v'hamasik,
all these are different verbs, but you know, for us it's all
like picking, you know, harvesting stuff. If you're a farmer, you got
a different verb for everything for everything different that you're doing. So
picking olives, which is מסיק, masik, האורה, ha'oreh, which is picking figs,
I think, okay, all of these things כולם מלאכה אחת הן, kulam
melacha achas hen, they are all one מלאכה. melacha. Again, right again
meaning that not even a תולדה, toldah, they're just all parallel אבות
מלאכות. avos melachos. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa,
האי מאן דשדא פיסא לדיקלא, hai man d'shada pissa l'dikla, somebody takes
a clump of dirt or like a rock and throws it against
a palm tree, ואתר תמרי, v'atar tamrei, and the dates fall. Now
that was what we were trying to do, right? And you were
trying to do that, yeah. חייב שתים, chayav shtayim, you do you
have you've done two. Two מלאכות, and again if it's בשוגג be-shogeg
you bring two קרבנות. korbanot. What is the two? אחת משום תולש
ואחת משום מפרק. Achat mishum tolesh v'achat mishum mefarek. The obvious one
is תולש, tolesh, which interesting, קוצר kotzer has now been abstracted because
קוצר kotzer means wheat, so we've abstracted it to תולש, tolesh, which
means picking something off, like removing something growing from where it's growing.
Okay, so while it started by calling it קוצר, kotzer, now it's
calling it תולש, tolesh, which is a little bit more of an
abstraction. But anyway, one for taking something down that is growing and
that you want the thing that you're removing. And the other is
מפרק. mefarek. Now מפרק mefarek is, Rashi says, I mean Tosafot says
a whole discussion, but simply it is basically like separating something.
And Rashi sees this as a תולדה toldah of דש. dash. When
you דש, dash, you thresh, you plow, you know, you thresh, you
push down on the kernel
on the whole thing and the husk comes off and the kernel
is removed. So similarly, for example, squeezing grapes, you know, you get
a juice out of a thing out of something it's contained within,
you know, you put some pressure on the thing and you remove
something from which it's contained within. So that's like סחיטה, sechita, מפרק,
mefarek, תולש. tolesh. Then there becomes a question about like milking cows,
because the גמרא Gemara says milking cows is מפרק, mefarek, which works
very good with this model, like you're removing some food from some
container thing if you think of it that way. תוספות Tosafot just
has a problem that we say in other places that מפרק mefarek
is only by things that grow from the ground and not from
animals. But presumably מפרק mefarek is a type of a דש, dash,
and again it's maybe this abstraction of דש, dash, and it's removing
food from things it's contained in. So why is this מפרק? mefarek?
So Rashi says because when dates grow, they grow in this big
cluster. I don't know, has somebody seen a date tree recently like
that? Okay, right, I thought so. Right, they grow like this big
surrounded what? Right, exactly, like grapes. So when you hit it, you
sort of are separating one off from the larger thing that it's
a part of. Now תוספות Tosafot says, yeah, but that doesn't surround
it. It's not like all these other examples about juice in a
grape or even milk in the udder of a cow. This is
just part of a group. It's not like the food is actually
surrounded by some outer shell. So תוספות Tosafot says what you're actually
doing are you are loosening it from the shell. Now do dates
grow with a shell around it? So I don't get it. תוספות
Tosafot says, so I'll read the lashon in תוספות, Tosafot, he says,
let me see this, ומשום דמחי של תמרים u-mishum de-machi shel temarim
he says שיש על התמרים קליפה העליונה. she-yesh al ha-temarim klipa ha-elyona.
This is the little one, ואחת משום מפרק. v'achat mishum mefarek. וכשמכה
בתמר מפרק את הקליפה
מן
התמרים.
u-kshemaka b'tamar mefarek et ha-klipa min
ha-temarim.
What? Attached to the stem? Yeah. There's a little part that's...
oh, you mean like right at the head of it. Yeah. Oh,
so that's what he is. The tiny little head that's at the
top of the stem. Anyway, somehow this is also מפרק. mefarek. Okay,
so he says that you do you get two for one. Similarly,
now notice that there's a parallel like the גמרא Gemara ended the
discussion about קוצר kotzer that you could be about זומר zomer that
you could be pruning and also do קוצר. kotzer. Here's the case
where you can get two for one. You can be תולש, tolesh,
קוצר, kotzer, and also מפרק.
mefarek. Nothing vis-a-vis the earth though, right? These are all vis-a-vis the
dates? חייב שתים. chayav shtayim.
Yeah, I thought the מפרק mefarek was about breaking the clod of
earth into...
oh, no, no, that's a good point, but no, that's not at
least that's not our Rashi or Tosafot.
Yeah, but isn't there a problem because you're משוה גומות? mashve gumot?
What are you משוה גומות? mashve gumot? If you hit a clod
of earth...
oh, yeah, I don't know, maybe it was a loose clod, maybe
it was a rock or whatever. Yeah, we're ignoring that part of
it. Okay, רב אשי אמר: Rav Ashi amar: אין דרך תלישה בכך
ואין דרך פריקה בכך. ein derech telisha b'kach v'ein derech prika b'kach.
We'll see this as debated again between רב פפא Rav Pappa and
רב אשי. Rav Ashi. He says, yeah, that's not the normal way
you do those things. So therefore it's a שינוי shinui and therefore
you're not חייב. chayav. Okay, and that becomes an interesting question about
how outside of the norm, you know, or how narrowly do we
define the norm, right? Like normally fine I pick it with my
hand, but by doing it this way, it's pretty effective, you know,
throwing it if I have a good aim, you know? So that's
an interesting question about how narrow or broad you define שינוי shinui
and I'll just tell you one interesting question about שינוי shinui is
does it have to be more difficult to do to be defined
as שינוי? shinui? Let's say for example, right, I turn on the
light switch with my right hand rather than my left. It's so
it's even though it's unusual... I'm a lefty, okay? Normal person they
do with their left instead of with their right. So even though
it's unusual, right, it's not doesn't make it any more difficult and
it also doesn't even impact the end result at all, right? So
how much, what is exactly the parameters of שינוי shinui is a
very important debate. We're going to see this between רב פפא Rav
Pappa and רב אשי Rav Ashi coming up more than once. Yeah,
Charlie, and then...
Charlie: So if I were to but if I were to write
with my left hand rather than the right?
That's the classic example of שינוי. shinui. Much more difficult and... right,
exactly. And that's a classic example, yes.
רב פפא Rav Pappa wants to give two חטאות Chata'os. because these
are two תולדות toldot of two different אבות? avot? Yes. If they
were two תולדות toldot of the same אבות?
avot, Right, one, no, one. Right, as long as everything is one
category, if it's an אב Av and a תולדה, Toldah two תולדות
toldos, in the same category, what I've been calling parallel אבות, Avs,
all of that is one חטאת. chatat. It has to be two
different categories, and then it doesn't matter, one תולדה toldah from one
and an אב av from another, it doesn't matter. Separate category, separate
חטאת. chatat. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, והמעמר. v'ha-m'amer. So
now we've cut the grain and now we're gathering it up like
Joseph. Same category, what I'm calling parallel אבות, all of that is
one חטאת. Chatas. It has to be two different categories and then
it doesn't matter, one תולדה toldah. from one and an אב av
from another, doesn't matter, separate categories, separate חטאות. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues, והמעמר. v'ha-me-amer. So now we've cut the grain and
now we're gathering it up like יוסף Yosef's dream. Okay, so מעמר.
me-amer. So this is probably what the easiest explanation of the מקושש
עצים mekoshish eitzim was, right, it was gathering up wood. But now,
what does it mean? It means like if your kids make a
mess with, you know, with toys, you can't gather them all up
and put them in the toy box? So let's take a look.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, said Rava, האי
מאן דכניף מלחא ממלחתא, hai man de-khanif milkha mi-milkhasa, if somebody gathers
up salt from a salt yard, or I don't know what exactly
what technically it's called, but anyway you have a place where you're
drying out sea water, I saw these by the Dead Sea, you
dry out sea water in order to get to evaporate the water
and then you have the salt, so then you have salt spread
throughout a large area and then you're gathering it up into clumps,
so it's very similar like, you know, grain is cut, apples fall
from the tree and you gather it up. Okay, so if somebody
does that, חייב משום מעמר, chayiv mishum me-amer, you're chayiv for gathering.
אביי אמר, Abaye amar, Abaye says, אין עימור אלא בגידולי קרקע. ein
imur ela b'gidulei karka. This is a very important limitation which sometimes
we say sometimes we don't, although classically all these things are done
here by things that grow from the ground, do we always limit
it to things that have grown from the ground? So as I
mentioned before there's that question about about מפרק, mifarek, דש, dash, because
does it apply like by cows, and by milking. So here though,
you know, Abaye makes that point. Yes it's similar, it's food, it's
a processing food, you're drying out the salt, after a certain stage
in the process you have to gather it, so it's actually quite
similar in terms of the idea of a stage of the processing
and then you're gathering it together, but it's not growing from the
ground. And at least עימור, imur, we haven't said this by other
things and we have to figure that out, but at least by
מעמר me-amer it's only by things growing from the ground. So now
you know that you can gather up the toys when your kids
make a mess, get them to clean it up, but okay whatever
it is. But the real issue is things that have fallen like
from things or picked off of things that have grown from the
ground. So actually, if you do have twigs that have fallen off
of trees and now you want to gather it for firewood, right,
that could be a perfect example of מעמר me-amer like the מקושש
עצים. mekoshish eitzim. So I mentioned this, this book is really great,
because I just think in general, pictures,
the 39 Melochos set.
No, obviously each one is doing a different function. Okay, but I
first of all I think visuals are great and I think that
it's just extremely well laid out, it has a lot of extremely
practical examples of each of the אב av. and practical דאורייתות De'oraisos
and דרבננות, De'rabbananos, right, and it's done very nicely, it's got in
the corners, it's got in the yeah, when we get to it
I'll show it to you. It's got in the corners the אב
av and then surrounding it it has like תולדות, toldos you know,
so here it has the guy that's plowing and then planting the
seeds, or not תולדות and practical implications: harvesting, gathering. So in the
example it gives here for gathering, it says piling scattered fruit in
an orchard, putting together a bouquet of flowers, okay, and so on.
Now the interesting thing it's got here because the other example it
has here is is stringing figs and it tells you it has
a little ספר תורה Sefer Torah if it's a דאורייתא de'oraisa, and
a little scroll of writing if it's a דרבנן. derabbanan It says
stringing figs, parenthesis, even at home. So while piling scattered fruit is
in the orchard, stringing figs is even at how much once it's
already been gathered and brought inside can you still do מעמר? me-amer?
Right, simply you would think only if it's there where it fell
and it hasn't yet been gathered and you know you can't like
have אין עימור אחר עימור, ein imur achar imur, you would think,
right, once it's been gathered and then, right. So anyway it is
interesting though because the stringing figs though was a way in which
they put it together in a very tight they made these like
balls of figs, right, but is that מעמר me-amer or not? So
that's interesting, you know, you can take a look there to see
the discussion,
but again I would this is I know it's for kids and
it's great for kids but I'd recommend it even for adults.
What if you had the figs and they fell out of the
bowl, putting them back in?
Yeah, no, no, no, this is only because it's a separate level
of bringing it together and it was also part of the processing
of this, at least in that time that's how they were brought
to get, you know, sold as that type of a bunch. But
anyway, but we haven't seen that, you can look there to see
the discussion. And he has the footnotes in the back of the
book to to give you all the מקורות, mekoros, lot a lot
of it is from משנה ברורה. Mishna Berurah. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues,
הדש, ha-dash, threshing. So again that they would have like an animal
walk over a almost like a a board with like cleats, as
it were, and it would press down on the piece on the
grain and it would get the it would get the kernel out
of the husk. So תנא, tana, הדש, ha-dash, whether it's threshing, המנפץ
ha-menapeitz which is combing
of flax to get out the seeds of it, והמנפת v'ha-menafet which
is combing of cotton to get out the seeds, כולהו מלאכה אחת
הן, kuleihu melacha achas hen, they're all one מלאכה. melacha Now I
have to tell you, that's interesting because on the one hand you
would say sure, it's all doing the same thing, it's getting the
kernel out of some surrounding stuff and it's just by different types
of objects: wheat, flax or whatever. But there's a difference because at
least as far as I understand, the purpose of the cotton and
of the flax is to clean the cotton and flax so that
you can have usable cotton and usable flax, not because you're interested
in the seeds. So רש"י Rashi actually says why isn't this a
תולדה toldah of, you know, מנפץ menapeitz by the wool? So he
says Well I can understand that sometimes things are limited, are defined
by the object they were done to. How much does object determine?
Well, right. Okay. Well, okay, yeah I know, that's true. Anyway, but
the problem is at least call it a תולדה. toldah. So maybe
it's similar in maybe it's similar in function that it's like, you
know, separating some kernel from the similar in sort of form, you
know, in terms of separating some kernel from the thing surrounding it,
but the goal is very different. Here it's to make the surrounding
thing usable, there it's to get the kernels out. And you know,
maybe also, maybe call it a תולדה toladah of something, maybe call
it a type of a בורר, borer, you know, again. So it's
very interesting that again it says it's in the category. At least
say it's a תולדה. toladah So here it says כולה מלאכה אחת
הן, kula melacha achat hen, which seems to be parallel אב. Sometimes
it's hard to understand exactly the categorization. Right, Charlie, yeah.
Today cotton seeds and flax seeds are now used for their oil.
They are. I don't know if that was the case back then.
So if you were doing it for that purpose then I assume
it is a direct parallel, yeah.
And for מנפץ menapetz was already
a different אב mentioned in one of these. Yeah, by wool, this
is by cotton or by flax, which is a seed,
not from the animal world. Okay, now we get to finally, you
know, again, as I said, it's a little frustrating, these huge categories
get one or two lines, but some of it gets developed later
in the מסכת. Now we're going to get to a place where
actually the גמרא Gemara will be a little more expansive to discuss
the parameters of a category which is בורר, borer, which is a
huge category for practical applications. הזורה hazoreh whether winnowing, הבורר haborer selecting
by hand. So you would winnow when you'd have the chaff and
the wheat, so separating the chaff from the wheat from the kernels,
you would throw it all up in the air after it's been
threshed and the wind would blow away the chaff and the denser
kernels would fall down. בורר borer is then after you select and
you get rid of various like dirt and stuff. Then you grind,
הטוחן, hatochan, and then you're מרקד, meraked, you sift. So the three
of them are all essentially separating good from bad. So the גמרא
Gemara says it: היינו זורה היינו בורר היינו מרקד, hainu zoreh hainu
borer hainu meraked, whether you know, winnowing, selecting, and sifting is all
essentially the same. אביי ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו, Abaye veRava damri tavaihu, אביי
Abaye and רבא Rava both say look: כל מילתא דהויא במשכן, kol
milta dehavya bamishkan, anything that was in the משכן, Mishkan. אף על
גב דאיכא דדמיא לה, af al gav de-ika dedamya leh, even though
there are other things that are similar to it, חשיב ליה, chashiv
leh, you get it gets a separate category. Yeah, you're right, conceptually
they're all the same, but each one of these was a different
process done in the משכן, so we're going to give it a
different category. Now part of what seems to be motivating this as
we'll see in a minute is that we got to get up
to thirty-nine. Okay, but we haven't said that yet. Okay, we just
said anything that happened in the משכן doesn't matter even if it's
conceptually the same. So the גמרא Gemara. says ולכתוב נמי כותש, velichtov
nami koteish, how about including also grinding? You add here, why don't
you have when you would take the wheat, you would want to
separate the bran from the rest of it, right, and you would
want to make fine flour, so you would bang it in a
like in a type of a hand grinder or something. So why
don't you so it
no, it would be different from the הטוחן, tochan, which would be
the fine grinding in order to make it into flour. There would
be like a previous grinding that would occur, I really maybe somebody
here knows better exactly how wheat made, but there's a I think
previously you do a type of a pounding and you remove the
bran. And then you do a fine grinding. Is that how you
make it? At what stage is the bran removed? Before you do
the fine grinding to make it into the flour?
Threshing removes the outer husk of the wheat kernel, pounding, which is
what you just talked about, removes the inner layer of bran still
attached to the kernel leaving the production of whiter flour.
That's what I said. That's what I said. I said you pounded
it to remove the bran.
Yeah, it's on the inside.
Yeah, okay. Right, I mean, okay, it's on the inside after the
husk. Right, okay, yeah, that's what I meant. Okay. So anyway, so
after you do the right, after you've removed the husk, but before
you do the fine grinding of the flour, if you want to
make fine flour and you don't want to have your bran as
part of it, you do a type of a pounding to remove
an inner shell to remove the bran. Okay, thank you. So then
the question is why don't we count that also? That happened, if
you're making fine flour. And okay, you'll tell me it's similar to
טחינה techina to the grinding because it's both pounding to remove something,
but you know, count it separately. So the גמרא Gemara. says or
ולכתוב נמי כותש, velichtov nami koteish, אמר אביי שכן עני אוכל פיתו
בלא כתישה. amar Abaye sheken ani ochel pitto belo ketisha. No, you
didn't always, you don't always do the pounding to remove the bran,
because people, you know, poor people don't eat fine flour, they eat
flour with bran. So therefore what? Big deal, it still was part
of the normal process. So רש"י Rashi says first of all there's
another question which is
which one which one do we want to include? What do you
think you want to include the pounding in? רש"י Rashi says we
want to include the pounding as a type of a טוחן Tochen
because it's basically pounding something and breaking it up. But you could
have said we should include it as a type of a בורר
Borer because it's to remove a part you don't want from a
part that you do want. So that's anyway just one question. But
anyway רש"י Rashi says that the answer is look, you know, and
then it really gets to this point about how much are these
thirty-nine like we knew exactly what the thirty-nine were. רש"י Rashi basically
says yeah, you know, we could have included it, but we're trying
to get a nice organizational principle here about making bread. And therefore
we only want to count the ones that are always done. And
since this isn't always done, we didn't want to include it in
the list. So meaning like there's no real objective reason it shouldn't
be one of the thirty-nine מלאכות, but you know what? It doesn't
really matter because it's included in טוחן Tochen anyway. So, you know,
why, since we're in an area here where it's really just going
to be duplication, so we're not going to bother to have a
duplicate category if it doesn't always exist. And we want to talk
about a normal process of making bread. Again, it really raises the
question about how much are, you know, is this idea of the
making bread a convenient organization and we could have organized it differently
and come up with a different number. And so that's what רש"י
Rashi says. רבא Rava says is the first answer. So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. רבא אמר, Rava amar,
רבא Rava says, האי מני רבי היא, Hai mani Rebi hi, דאמר
אבות מלאכות ארבעים חסר אחת. de'amar Avot Melachot Arbayim Chaser Achas. This
is רבי Rebi that says there's only thirty-nine. Like was I thinking
otherwise? It sounds like before I could have had yeah, I could
have had forty מלאכות, forty-one, forty-two. It's just that it wasn't in
the process, it wasn't always in the process of bread, so I
chose not to mention it. He says no, no, no, we're limited
by thirty-nine. ואי חשיב כותש, Ve'i chashiv Kotesh, and if we're counting
that, הוו להו ארבעים, havu lehu Arbayim, then it would have been
forty. So, you know, we I sort of, as you sort of
assume that that was part of what was informing the discussion until
now, but it seems surprisingly that the גמרא Gemara thinks it's possible
you could have not that oh, this is רבי Rebi who says
there's only thirty-nine. What, somebody says another number? It sounds like there's
a possibility it could have been more. It's just yeah, we didn't
want to mention it. Okay. Oh, no, no, we had
to limit it. וליפוק חדא מהנך ולעייל כותש? Velifuk chada mehanach vela'ayel
Kotesh? Okay, still doesn't explain why we didn't, why you know why
why we had three types of בורר Borer and we only mentioned
and we didn't mention כותש. Kotesh. It doesn't explain why you know
we had we had a triple of that and we only had
once this, and רש"י Rashi says particularly if כותש Kotesh is a
type of a טוחן, Tochen, so he has two types of בורר
Borer and two types of טוחן. Tochen. Why do we have a
three and a one? Why not have כותש Kotesh and not one
of the other ones? אלא מחוורתא כדאביי. Ela mechvarta ke'Abaye. It's better
like אביי Abaye said, which is, is that it's not always part
of the process of bread. Of course again it's very funny because
they didn't make bread in the, in the making of the משכן.
רש"י Rashi says all of these things about cooking were really processes
they did for making the spices and the, not the spices, the,
the dyes, the plants that they were going to extract the dye.
So it's very funny. Well, yeah, that's true. That's really what was
in the משכן. But as a convenient organizational principle, we give, we
define it in terms of bread even though that wasn't exactly what
was in the משכן. And since in the bread you didn't have
this part of the process all the time we're not going to
mention it but we'll mention other things even though it's really a
three times repetition. So it really does seem although the גמרא Gemara
seems to sideline the issue of the thirty-nine that that's also playing
a role, that we gotta get up to thirty-nine and somehow we
could have easily have organized it slightly differently. But again, that's if
we're talking about duplicates. If it's duplicates it doesn't really matter whether
we duplicate this way or duplicate that way. It's just a way
to get to thirty-nine. Charlie isn't there micro?
Everything changed back then, poor people ate whole wheat bread now
rich...
right, whole wheat bread is more expensive now. Or it's just I
know that it's something, yeah, the health thing, yes.
So basically רש"י Rashi would have to contend they were still doing
זורה Zoreh for like just plants for dye even though not for
wheat. There's chaff and there's all that?
Presumably. רש"י Rashi doesn't always spell that out but he would have
to say that yeah. And that is strange. Right, like why, you
know, to figure out if you had if every one of these
processes occurred when you were dealing with the types of plants that
would produce dye.
One more thing to say, no, you know wheat is because they
use
לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim and it's not, no, that is a position
of one of the גאונים Geonim that is not רש"י. Rashi's.
But I'm saying if you don't
hold רש"י Rashi they do. Yeah, the right. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabbanan. Now we continue. Now we finally get to and beyond the
category defining what exactly defines בורר. Borer. And I should also by
the way say that even though the גמרא has said that these
are duplicate, we will find when we get to like מרקד Merakeid
that there are some differences in its parameters from that of בורר.
Borer. So so much for being an exact duplicate. Anyway. תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan. היו לפניו מיני אוכלים. Hayu lefanav minei ochlin. Now we
get to the real הלכות Halachos of what defines בורר. Borer. You
have in front of you a number of different food stuffs. בורר
ואוכל בורר ומניח. Borer ve'ochel Borer u'maniach.
You can take and eat, you can take and put it down.
Sounds like you can sort of leave it for later so it
doesn't mean you can put it down in front of somebody else.
ולא יבור. Velo yavor. But don't do בורר. Borer. ואם בירר חייב
חטאת. Ve'im beirer chayav chatas. And if you do בורר Borer you
have to bring a sin offering. So what are you talking? מאי
קאמר? Mai ka'amar? What does he say, what are you saying? You
can do it but don't do it. So אמר עולא, Amar Ulla,
and now because this is very vague we're going to get three
different approaches of sticking criteria into this. This is what you can
do, this is what you can't, but you know it's missing the
keyword what. makes the difference what you can and can't, and three
different approaches to sticking in that key criterion. So let's take a
look. אמר עולא amar Ulla says עולא, Ulla, הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar,
this is what it's saying. בורר ואוכל לבו ביום, borer v'ocheil l'vo
bayom, you can separate out if you're going to eat later that
day, so you can do בורר, borer, you know, separate the wheat
from the chaff or whatever, the good from the bad if you'll
eat later that day. ובורר ומניח לבו ביום, u'vorer u'maniach l'vo bayom,
and you can set it aside, meaning again Tosafot says that means
for somebody else if it's going to be eaten later that day.
ולמחר לא
יבור, u'l'machar lo yivror, but you can't do it for tomorrow. ואם
בירר, v'im beirer, and if you did it for the sake of
tomorrow, חייב חטאת, chayav chatas, then it's a sin offering. מתקיף לה
רב חסדא, maskif lah Rav Chisda, רב חסדא Rav Chisda asked on
this. וכי מותר לאפות לבו ביום? v'chi mutar l'afos l'vo bayom? I
don't get it. Can you bake for today? וכי מותר לבשל לבו
ביום? v'chi mutar l'vashel l'vo bayom? Can you cook for today? How
does doing it for today make a difference? Now there's an obvious
answer to this, which is, and the implicit thing going on here
that Tosafot himself says is, look at the little Tosafot, וכי מותר
לאפות פחות מכשיעור, v'chi mutar l'afos pachas m'kishiur, well, actually it's going
on later, but we'll get to that in a minute, but he
says והמותר סלקא דעתך דפחות מכשיעור הוי דרך אכילה. v'hamutar salka daitach
d'pachas m'kishiur havei derech achila. The point is like this, that there
are some types of ways that you do בורר borer in the
process of eating, right, that as you're eating things, you know,
you're always doing בורר borer at some type of a level, right?
So, you know, and how can you, by the way, cut your
food? Why isn't that מחתך? mechatech? And how can you know, so
at what stage do you define that what you're doing is actually
eating and not some type of food preparation, which is really what
בורר borer is, like preparation. Fish bone gets very complicated, we'll get
to that anyway, yeah, okay, so big Mishnah Berurah about fish bones.
Anyway, so the point is defining the line
between בורר, borer, which is more about preparation and act of eating.
Okay, think about peeling an orange also, right, other than, anyway. So
one explanation is, well, if you're going to have it later that
day, that's not like classic בורר borer is done out in the
field, it's at an early stage of preparation. So if it's for
the future, then you call it preparation. If it's for today, you'll
call it part of the eating process. Gemara says, that I don't
buy. Later today you're not—it doesn't exist part of the act of
eating, so that gets rejected.
אלא אמר רב חסדא, ela amar Rav Chisda, says רב חסדא, Rav
Chisda, בורר ואוכל פחות מכשיעור, borer v'ocheil pachas m'kishiur, בורר ומניח פחות
מכשיעור. borer u'maniach pachas m'kishiur. You can do less than the minimum
amount. The classic minimum amount by foodstuff is a כגרוגרת, kigrogeres, which
is like a dried, what is it, dried fig. Thank you. וכשיעור
לא יבור, v'kishiur lo yivror, don't do the minimum amount, ואם בירר
חייב חטאת, v'im beirer chayav chatas, and then if you did, then
you violated and are חייב חטאת. chayav chatas. מתקיף לה רב יוסף,
maskif lah Rav Yosef, same question. וכי מותר לאפות פחות מכשיעור? v'chi
mutar l'afos pachas m'kishiur? I don't get it. Can you bake less
than the minimum amount? So, and now by the way, Rashi, we
discussed פחות מכשיעור pachas m'kishiur yesterday.
Rashi says here that it's an איסור דאורייתא issur d'oraisa of חצי
שיעור. chatzi shiur. There actually is a debate, this idea of חצי
שיעור chatzi shiur that's discussed by eating, eating less than a minimum
amount of prohibited food or on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. And the
Gemara says there that it's a biblical—not the same biblical prohibition, but
it is a biblical prohibition. Here the Gemara just says, since when
are you allowed to do it? But it's actually some question whether
the idea of פחות מכשיעור pachas m'kishiur applies by non—by מצוות mitzvos
that aren't related to eating. Anyway, but Rashi does say that here.
So anyway, so again, what was he thinking? So as Tosafot tells
us, he was thinking that if you only do a little bit
at a time, that's eating, that's not בורר, borer, that's eating. But
no, that gets challenged, that's not defined by quantity. אלא אמר רב
יוסף, ela amar Rav Yosef, בורר ואוכל ביד, borer v'ocheil b'yad, בורר
ומניח ביד. borer u'maniach b'yad. You can use your hand, right? If
it's being done with a hand, not a professional tool, then that
is part of how you eat, by just separating things out or
whatever, that's eating if you use your hand. Maybe also this is
an issue of שינוי, shinnuy, but it's—it's either defined in שינוי shinnuy
or defining again a process of eating. בקנון ובתמחוי לא יבור, b'kanun
u'v'tamchui lo yivror, don't use a type of a funnel or a
large dish, which maybe helps you in the process but it's not
really the professional vessel to use. ואם בירר פטור אבל אסור, v'im
beirer patur aval assur, but if you do that you're exempt, but
it's not allowed because it's a שינוי shinnuy maybe, but it doesn't
make it מותר. mutar. ובנפה ובכברה לא יבור, u'vinfa u'v'khvara lo yivror,
however, you should certainly not use a sieve or type of a,
what's it called, a sifter or such different types of things that
are like used for that, you know, for separating. ואם בירר חייב
חטאת, v'im beirer chayav chatas, and if you do that, use a
professional vessel, then you are חייב חטאת. chayav chatas. So that's a
very logical explanation, it's degree of שינוי shinnuy and plus maybe דרך
אכילה. derech achila. Gemara says, that makes sense why that would be
מותר. mutar. Well, we're not—I will discuss later how these different criteria
work together. Now each one is focusing on just their own personal
criterion. I understand. מתקיף לה רב המנונא, maskif lah Rav Hamnuna, רב
המנונא Rav Hamnuna said, מידי קנון ותמחוי תני? midi kanun v'tamchui tani?
I don't get it. If—since when does it, you know, it doesn't
say this idea of the plate and the funnel. Now of course
it doesn't say any of this, but Tosafot says, yeah, but if
you're saying there's going to be three levels, not just an either-or,
hands versus vessel, today versus tomorrow, but three levels, you know, מותר,
mutar, פטור אבל אסור, patur aval assur, completely then חייב חטאת, chayav
chatas, you need to have been more
specific.
Okay,
reason why מותר mutar or not
allowed. vessel is biblical. So if you're going to have three different
levels based on the specific vessel, it's not just either-or, you should
say what the vessel is. אלא אמר רב הונא, Ella amar Rav
Huna, רב הונא Rav Huna says here's the difference: בורר ואוכל, אוכל
מתוך פסולת. Borer v'ochel, ochel mitoch psoles. You can take out the
food from the chaff because that again is not the normal way
and maybe also it's דרך אכילה, derech achila, that's the normal way
of eating is you focus on the food and you take the
food. בורר ומניח, אוכל מתוך פסולת, Borer u'maniach, ochel mitoch psoles, or
you can give it to somebody, remove the food from the chaff.
בורר ומניח, אוכל מתוך פסולת, Borer u'maniach, ochel mitoch psoles, I just
said that. פסולת מתוך אוכל לא יברור, Psoles mitoch ochel lo yivror,
however the chaff from the food, that you cannot do. ואם ברר
חייב חטאת, V'im birer chayav chatas, and if so, then you are
חייב חטאת chayav chatas because that again is not the normal way
of eating and that is the normal way of selecting. So מתקיף
לה אביי, Matkif lah Abaye, אביי Abaye said: מידי אוכל מתוך פסולת
קתני? Midi ochel mitoch psoles katani? Again, it doesn't say the key
lines, it doesn't say food from chaff, chaff from food, doesn't say
anything. So אלא אמר אביי, Ella amar Abaye, or אביי, Abaye, I
don't know how we're going to get an answer, it doesn't say
the keywords. So אביי Abaye says: בורר ואוכל לאלתר ובורר ומניח לאלתר.
Borer v'ochel l'alter u'borer u'maniach l'alter. You can do it, it's a
variation of the first answer, but it means immediately. If you are
selecting and eating immediately, that's eating, that's not בורר. borer. ובו ביום
לא יברור, U'vo bayom lo yivror, don't do it for later in
the day, ואם ברר, v'im birer, and if you did do it
for the later in the day, נעשה כבורר לאוצר, na'asah k'borer l'otzar,
that's like the paradigm בורר. borer. What's the paradigm בורר? borer? You're
selecting to go into the warehouse. It's an early stage of preparation.
So anything that is later than immediate, what's immediate we'll discuss, but
even if it's later that day, that is the biblical בורר borer
and חייב חטאת. chayav chatas. And you're חייב חטאת. chayav chatas. Now
again, why it does not say, it also doesn't say that key
line, but perhaps it's implied by the אוכל. ochel.
Right,
exactly. So since it says בורר ואוכל, borer v'ochel, that implies the
immediate. That at least has some. I know, so that's why תוספות
Tosafos says מניח maniach doesn't mean מניח maniach for later, מניח maniach
means put in front of your guest. But yes, at least אביי
Abaye could claim, as תוספות Tosafos correctly said, that the אוכל ochel
suggests that. Now, what we have here is basically put out three
criteria. We have אוכל מתוך פסולת, ochel mitoch psoles, we have food
from the chaff. We have ביד b'yad versus a vessel. And we
have immediate. Now, the third one, which is today versus tomorrow, seems
to be completely rejected and replaced by a similar idea but a
much narrower definition of immediate versus later. So first question is how
immediate is immediate? The general definition that's adopted, you know, the ראש
Rosh quotes or whatever, is that anything that will be for like
later in the meal, the normal amount of time that like, that
it's, so basically the normal way you define it is the time
that you begin that you prepare things right before a meal and
it's going to be for later that meal, even for the end
of the meal. So let's say you expect your meal to last
an hour, right? And you know you're going to have something for
the dessert. So not like the early preparations you do, but sometimes
there's time right before the meal starts that you do some last
minute preparations. So right? So the amount of time, let's say that's
twenty minutes before the meal you do last minute preparations and it'll
be eaten later in the meal, so up to like let's say
an hour later, like that's sort of seen as within the context
of the part of the process of eating, דרך אכילה. derech achila.
So that one though, that is לאלתר. l'alter. Again, don't take any
פסק הלכה psak halacha from what I'm saying. You want to talk
about פסק הלכה, psak halacha, we'll do that another time. I'm going
to give you some basic parameters. The bigger, more important question: so
the גמרא seems to settle on אביי, Abaye, but we're about to
see that it's going to go back and discuss the other criteria
as well. And the big key question are these criteria "and's" or
"or's"? Okay, because the גמרא doesn't reject these other ideas. So is
it that in order for it to be מותר, muttar, you need
it to be both אוכל ochel and ביד b'yad and לאלתר? l'alter?
Or is it maybe like any two of those make it מותר,
muttar, or maybe any one of those make it מותר? muttar? So
no big surprise, the basic assumption is you need all three of
those to make it מותר. muttar. Now, you would have thought, okay,
maybe I need all three to make it מותר, muttar, but maybe
if I have two out of the three, at least it's like
only דרבנן, it's not דאורייתא. de'oraisa But there also tends to be
an assumption that if you're missing any one of them, it becomes
a דאורייתא חייב. de'oraisa chayav. So the absolute hard you know most
strict reading of this גמרא. It's not explicit. We're going to see
now some cases, but that is where the הלכה halacha winds up.
Yes.
Just make sure I understood what you said because about immediacy. It
depends on the meal? I mean like you know if you're in
שול shul before.
Yeah, yeah, no, that not. It's right in the immediate. Anyway, I'm
not going to talk about specific. Okay, so let's take a look
at the גמרא. אמרו רבנן קמיה דרבא. Amru rabbanan kamei d'Rava.
So the rabbis said in front of רבא Rava about אביי's Abaye
re-explanation that it was about immediate versus later. אמר להו, Amar lehu,
he said to them, like the rabbinic students, שפיר אמר נחמני. Shapir
amar Nachmani. נחמני, Nachmani, which was אביי's Abaye like you know name.
רבא Rava said oh, that was a good explanation. That's good פשט.
pshat. Okay. Agreeing on something? Yes, exactly. Now, היו לפניו שני מיני
אוכלין. Hayu l'fanav shenei minei ochlin.
Now here comes another interesting idea. I mean there's like you know
tons and tons of stuff written on every single criterion point here.
Because here it says two types of food, which means you can
even have בורר borer by something that's not objectively פסולת psoles if
it's just a type of food you're not interested in. interested in.
So you've got carrots and peas and you don't like the carrots.
So by selecting out the carrots that's בורר borer even though carrots
are totally fine whatever because you don't like. Now somebody else likes
it if Michael here likes carrots and I don't, I take out
the carrots and say here Michael have some carrots. So that actually
is a way that it's okay because I'm giving it to him
and for him it's אוכל. ochel. But it is possible to have
cases of פסולת psolet because subjectively for you it's פסולת. psolet. Same
food group?
No, that's a good question. If it's all types of the same
type of food then it might not be unless it's something like
really rotten. But let's say
you got your white meat and your dark meat or what were
you going to say?
I was going to say like two variations of a kind of
fruit.
Yeah. So there are some degrees to which at a certain point
we say that if it's מין אחד min echad it's a point
where we don't say that it's not a problem. The question of
shells of something versus the thing itself. Anyway, so now the גמרא
said but that actually is a limitation on this. היו לפניו שני
מיני אוכלין. hayu lefanav shenei minei ochlin. You have two types of
food. ובירר ואכל ובירר והניח. u-virer ve-achal u-virer ve-hiniach. And you went
ahead and you did this. You separated out and you ate. So
that should be just like we described. If it means immediate, then
it should be fine. That phrase we used before which said it
was allowed. רב אשי מתני פטור. Rav Ashi matni patur. רב אשי
Rav Ashi says you're exempt. רבי ירמיה מדפתי מתני חייב. Rabbi Yirmeya
mi-Difti matni chayav. רבי ירמיה מדפתי Rabbi Yirmeya mi-Difti says you're liable.
רב אשי מתני פטור והתניא חייב. Rav Ashi matni patur ve-hatanya chayav.
Don't we say liable? I mean the second part of the ברייתא
Braita before. The first part said מותר, mutar, said you could do
it. But okay, anyway, the גמרא is just getting back to this
issue about what are the parameters. לא קשיא. lo kashya. It's not
difficult. הא בכנון ותמחוי הא בנפה וכברה. ha be-kanon ve-tamchuy ha be-nafa
u-kevara. That... oh because he said פטור. patur. If he had said
מותר mutar I would have assumed that he meant the scenario in
which it was totally מותר. mutar. But what's an example... right your
hand and immediate... but what's an example that it's פטור? patur? It's
a middle case. So the only case we had so far that
puts it in the middle is when you use a vessel but
not the standard vessel. So use some type of a funnel but
it's not a sieve. That's in the פטור patur category. So you
see although we emphasize the immediate we haven't forgotten this other criterion
of what type of a vessel. And then it raises the question
are you having all the criteria, one of the criteria, how's it
working? Okay. כי אתא רב דימי אמר ki ata Rav Dimi amar
when רב דימי Rav Dimi said שבתא דרב ביבי הוי, shabta de-Rav
Bibi havay, it was the שבת Shabbos? of רב ביבי Rav Bibi
which רש"י Rashi says means it was רב ביבי'ס Rav Bibi's turn
to attend to the rabbis. ואיקלע רבי אמי ורבי אסי ve-ikla Rabbi
Ami ve-Rabbi Assi and רבי אמי Rabbi Ami and רבי אסי Rabbi
Assi came to visit and he was supposed to bring them some
food. שדא קמייהו כלכלה דפירי. shada kammaihu kalkala de-firi.
So he threw in front of them a basket of fruit. Like
he poured it out in front of them and they could take
what they wanted and presumably now you could say maybe it was
an issue of selecting good fruit from bad fruit which gets to
the two types of food. Could be. רש"י Rashi says also there
were like leaves mixed up in it and it was about selecting
the leaves, getting them removed from the leaves. Okay. ולא ידענא ve-lo
yadana and I don't know אם משום דסבר אוכל מתוך
פסולת אסור. im mishum de-savar ochel mi-toch psolet assur. Why didn't he
just select the food directly? Maybe he thinks even אוכל מתוך פסולת
ochel mi-toch psolet is forbidden. Okay, which is maybe that's why he
didn't do it ahead of time. Now that's bizarre because until now
we said it's okay. But
תוספות Tosafot says... wait a minute... right. Because תוספות Tosafot says because
it would have been not לאלתר. le'alter. So maybe the reason he
didn't do it beforehand is because he thinks that when it's not
לאלתר, le'alter, when it's not immediate, even אוכל מתוך פסולת ochel mi-toch
psolet is no good. אי משום עין יפה הוא דמכוין i mishum
ayin yafa hu de-michavein or maybe just wanted to do it because
it looks generous putting it all in front of them and letting
them select. So I don't know exactly why he did it that
way. But again what we are doing is notice what we have
very subtly done. Right after saying that אביי Abaye was right that
it has to do with immediate versus later, we immediately introduced the
other two criteria. We introduced this idea
about the נפה nafa and the כברה, kevara, don't forget... I mean
about the כנון kanon and the תמחוי. tamchuy. Right? We had רב
אשי Rav Ashi or whoever it was said it's פטור אבל אסור
patur aval assur if you use a wrong type of vessel. Then
we have this story that reminds us about the אוכל מתוך פסולת
ochel mi-toch psolet versus the פסולת מתוך אוכל. psolet mi-toch ochel. So
all three of those criteria remain in place. Okay. למימרא כסבר... חזקיה
אמר. Chizkiya amar. חזקיה Chizkiya says הבורר תורמוסין מתוך פסולת שלהן חייב.
ha-borer turmusin mi-toch psolet shelahen chayav.
If you remove like these are some type of legumes. How do
they translate it there? Lupines. Lupines. There's a picture. Okay, I can't
see the picture. But anyway what is it? Some type of a
legume. Anyway. That's right. From their shells, חייב. chayav. You're liable. Now
that's bizarre. That's אוכל מתוך פסולת. ochel mi-toch psolet. Presumably it's with
your hand. Why would he be חייב? chayav? So למימרא כסבר חזקיה
אוכל מתוך פסולת אסור? le-meimra kasavar Chizkiya ochel mi-toch psolet assur? Is
he saying even אוכל ochel from פסולת psolet is forbidden? Says no.
שאני תורמוסין דשלקי להו שבע זימני. shani turmusin de-shalkei lehu sheva zimni.
These lupines are different because you boil them seven times. ואי לא
שלקי להו מסרח ve-i lo shalkei lehu masrach and if you don't
do it... or שלקי... shalkei... there's a question about the גירסא. girsa.
If you don't boil it more or if you don't remove it
now it'll get spoiled. וכפסולת מתוך אוכל דמי. u-ke-psolet mi-toch ochel dami.
It's like פסולת psolet from אוכל. ochel. So there's a big רש"י
Rashi trying to figure out what it means.
Something along the lines that
you are that right now you've boiled it so much and when
you try to remove the actual seeds they get like mushy. So
the seeds of themselves somehow type even though this is you're doing
it intentionally for this. some type of a פסולת psolos where the
stuff you haven't yet handled isn't mushy, and therefore even though you're
removing the food and leaving the פסולת psolos behind, in some way
it's seen as פסולת psolos from אוכל ochel because to some degree
it's mushy from the non-mushy. I, yeah, well I lost me too.
Okay, I mean I'm just repeating what more or less what רשי
Rashi said. There's a couple of explanations, but nobody really understands it.
I mean I wouldn't say nobody. It's hard to understand this. You're
דוקא davka doing it for the sake of the stuff, but somehow
in this context the thing you're removing was also a little yichy
and mushy, so therefore it's like פסולת psolos from אוכל. ochel. Look,
if you wanted to say דרבנן it was אסור assur that's one
thing, what's really hard to understand is that he says חייב. chayav.
But we'll leave it at that and let's try to get a
little bit further. Yeah, that's a bit loopy. Yeah, don't worry if
it's not loopy you don't have to worry about it. Okay, וטוחן,
Vatochen, אמר רב פפא. Amar Rav Pappa. Now we get to grinding.
Now this becomes also a very important, very important issue. האי מאן
דפריס סילקא, Hai man defaris silka, somebody that chops up, רשי Rashi
says, מינצי, mintsei, minces a beet, חייב משום טוחן chayav mishum tochen
is חייב chayav for טוחן. tochen. Now what the heck? You are
cutting up food into little pieces? So if you take a look
at תוספות, Tosafos, האי מאן דפריס סילקא, Hai man defaris silka, דוקא
בסילקא, davka besilka, only by beets, שייך טחינה, shayach techina, אבל שאר
אוכלין שרי. aval shear ochlin sharei. So what makes beets special? So
maybe it's that because they're normally not eaten raw and if you
make it into very fine then maybe sometimes you'll be making it
through some type of a transformation. Anyway, the ראש Rosh gives another
explanation which is this is not beets at all, what you have...
it's not סילקא silka he read it סילתא silta and which we're
coming up to in a minute and what you've really done is
you've turned something into like a sawdust or you've taken some type
of a plant and you've removed the leaves and you've turned something
into almost like a dust-like thing. Because basically he says, since when
can you not cut up food? Right? If you're allowed to cut
food, what, you know, what exactly is the size that it stops
being cutting and it starts becoming grinding? So it's one thing when
you transform something from like a solid like a grain into like
a type of a dust, right? That's not just, you know, that's
really actually not just tiny little pieces of the same thing but
it's actually a real transformation. But to chop something up into tiny
pieces, why is that a מלאכה? Nevertheless, רשי Rashi here says that
that's what the גמרא is talking about. תוספות Tosafos wants to limit
it to beets without explaining why but at least it puts it
in a box and like before like the lupine, fine, don't do
it with beets. But this does become an issue about cutting things
up smallie, smallie, cutting things up in very tiny pieces and is
that considered to be טוחן? tochen? So there's a whole interesting question
I ask my students when we're learning הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbos about
can you make, can you make egg salad, exactly, on שבת? Shabbos
So you have to discuss chopping up the stuff very fine, you
have to discuss adding the mayonnaise, a type of לש, losh, all
these things. Anyway there's a long תשובה teshuva and I think the
ציץ אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer that says we've been making egg salad for
hundreds of years on שבת Shabbos and he explains why it's allowed
and one important question is A, is it טוחן tochen at all
when you do mince up food? And number two is maybe the
same way by בורר borer it's allowed immediately in the context of
eating and לאלתר, le'alter, maybe that should become a factor as well
by טוחן. tochen. So if you're making the egg salad right before
the meal then you have also the לאלתר le'alter category but this
is quite shocking this line if it's סילקא silka if it refers
to a beet. Okay, so let's just read up to the next
two dots. אמר רב מנשיא, Amar Rav Menashya, סבר רב מנשיא, sevar
Rav Menashya, האי מאן דסלית סילתי, hai man desalis silti, now it's
about if you make sawdust, חייב משום טוחן. chayav mishum tochen. Now
that makes sense. You're really... it's a much bigger physical transformation and
you're turning it from like into a powder from a solid, okay,
and therefore you're חייב chayav even though it's not food, which is
interesting. It does grow from the ground but it's not food but
nevertheless that's טוחן. tochen. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, אי קפיד
אמשחתא, ei kapid amishchata, now if you're cutting the wood and you
care about the exact size of it, חייב משום מחתך, chayav mishum
mechatech, you're also חייב chayav for cutting. As I mentioned to you
the other day and we'll talk about this, there's two similar but
very distinct categories. קורע, Koreia, tearing, which is not about caring about
the size, any type of tearing but it's limited to... I mean
that's productive, that's constructive, it's limited to cloth. Then you have מחתך
mechatech which applied by leather which is not limited to the type
of material, applies to leather, applies to wood, applies to anything. So
what? Like tearing a napkin is a מלאכה? No. There it's when
it's done, this is a very key
criterion, קפיד אמשחתא, kapid amishchata, that you want, you're very concerned about
the exact size and you're cutting it so it should be a
very specific type of a size. Then you have מחתך mechatech applies
to other materials but it does have this key criterion of קפיד
אמשחתא. kapid amishchata. So we'll continue tomorrow with the other categories of
the מלאכה.
So I want to understand are you allowed to mince up garlic
in the end or not?
Hmm? Are you allowed to mince up fine? What? Are you allowed
to mince up garlic? I wouldn't do it unless it was לאלתר.
le'alter.
What?
I would dice. Mincing is smaller than dicing, right? Yes. Yeah, I
would dice not mince.
Rabbi Twersky would make himself make the egg salad on the שבת
Shabbos table and then immediately eat it.
He'd do it on the שבת Shabbos table? Yeah, that's what his
Sussman does.
Oh yeah? Talk about it. Yeah, there it is.
I guess maybe
that's a חסידיש Chassidish מנהג. minhag. Okay, so
דש. dash. We said דש dash is the next one. Squeezing. Right?
So the מלאכה of דש dash is normally threshing. It's taking the
grain out of the husk. That is the אב מלאכה. av melacha.
But the תולדה toladah. of דש dash is called סחיטה, sechitah, which
is squeezing a fruit for its juice. And the reason why it's
a תולדה is because you're doing the same thing. You're extracting the
good from the bad, or the good from the container. It's just
a different venue. Threshing is in the field, and squeezing is in
the kitchen. So because of the change of venue, it's a תולדה.
Now, דאורייתא, de'oraisa. the only two fruits that are דאורייתא are olives
and grapes. Why? Because historically, that's what those fruits were for. They
were for their juice. You squeeze an olive for oil, you squeeze
a grape for wine. Other fruits are מדרבנן. miderabanan. Unless it's a
place where it's common to squeeze them. Like in America, we squeeze
oranges. So in America, squeezing an orange would be דאורייתא. Now, what
about a lemon? A lemon is interesting because you don't drink lemon
juice. You use it to flavor food. So the הלכה halacha is
that you can squeeze a lemon on שבת directly onto the food.
Why? Because the liquid is being absorbed into the food and becomes
part of it. It's called משקה הבא לאוכל כאוכל דמי. mashke haba
le'ochel ke'ochel dami. However, you can't squeeze a lemon into an empty
cup because then you're making a liquid. So that's סחיטה, sechitah, even
though it's מדרבנן. miderabanan. But squeezing onto the fish, that's מותר. mutar.